<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "../dtd/concept.dtd" []>
<concept id="concept-dylan-file-naming-conventions">
  <title>File naming conventions</title>
  <prolog>
    <copyright>
      <copyryear year="1995-2004"/>
      <copyrholder>Functional Objects, Inc.</copyrholder>
    </copyright>
  </prolog>
  <conbody>
    <section>
      <p>In practice, importing a source distribution into a Dylan
      program involves unpacking the source distribution into its own
      subtree and then informing the environment of the location of
      the tree root. The environment then walks the entire subtree
      locating LID files, which describe the libraries in the
      distribution by giving a name to, and designating the source
      files associated with, each library. </p>

      <p>Importing a Dylan program into the environment in this way
      requires two things:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>That the LID files in the distribution can be identified.</li>

	<li>That the file designators supplied to the
        <codeph>Files:</codeph> keyword in LID files can be mapped to
        the corresponding source filenames on disk.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>If you are importing files from a platform that does not
      insist on, or conventionally use, standard filename suffixes to
      identify the filetype (such as MacOS), then you must rename your
      source files as follows:</p>

      <ul>
	<li>LID files must be given filenames with the suffix
	<filepath>.lid</filepath>.</li>

        <li>Dylan source files must be given filenames with the suffix
        <filepath>.dylan</filepath> or <filepath>.dyl</filepath>.</li>
      </ul>

      <p>The file designators that appear in LID files may be a string
      of characters of any length, constructed from the set of hyphen,
      underscore, and the mixed-case alphanumeric characters. Note
      that you do not have to specify the source filename suffix as
      part of the filename designator. This ensures that the LID files
      themselves do not need to be edited when importing source code
      from a platform such as MacOS that does not insist on particular
      filename suffixes to specify the file type.</p>

      <p>The name of a LID file is not significant, and in particular
      need not be the same as the library name. Hierarchical directory
      structure can be used to organize multi-library systems as long
      as the files directly associated with each library are in a
      single directory.</p>
    </section>
  </conbody>
</concept>
