<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd" []>
<concept id="dylan-library-catalog">
  <title>Dylan Library Catalog</title>
  <conbody>
    <p>A Dylan Library Catalog is a collection of XML files containing
    metadata concerning software libraries written in the Dylan
    programming language.  The metadata includes information useful to
    both the compiler and to human users, and includes:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Human-readable short titles and long descriptions.</li>

      <li>Copyright and redistribution license information.</li>

      <li>Library taxonomy information, placing libraries into
      conceptual categories.</li>

      <li>Specifications of where the compiler and development
      environment can locate databases and compiled libraries for
      binary-only projects.</li>

      <li>Specifications of where the compiler can locate project
      files (and sources) for libraries it opens.  </li>

      <li>Specifications of where the compiler and development
      environment should place intermediate build files, compiler
      databases, compiled libraries, and profiling information for
      libraries built from source code.</li>

      <li>Specifications of whether certain libraries should be
      treated as “system” libraries (treated as read-only, and for
      which certain types of information should be hidden) or “user”
      libraries (subject to recompilation when necessary).</li>
    </ul>

    <p>A Dylan Library Catalog file can incorporate another catalog by
    reference, optionally overriding its settings with its own.  This
    allows users to control excactly which libraries the compiler sees
    and how it treats them according to their own preferences.</p>

    <p>Additionally, a Dylan Library Catalog file can refer to a
    library catalog retrieved from a remote URI.  This allows a Dylan
    compiler to, at the user&apos;s option, automatically retrieve and
    install Dylan libraries as they are needed for compilation.</p>

    <p>The Dylan Library Catalog facility was designed as a
    replacement for the Registry and Dylan Library Pack facilities of
    the Open Dylan compiler, and to alleviate the extensive use of
    <option>-L</option> options with the Gwydion Dylan
    <cmdname>d2c</cmdname> compiler.</p>
  </conbody>
</concept>
