<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "../dtd/concept.dtd" []>
<concept id="concept-lid-files">
  <title>LID Files</title>
  <prolog>
    <copyright>
      <copyryear year="1995-2004"/>
      <copyrholder>Functional Objects, Inc.</copyrholder>
    </copyright>
  </prolog>
  <conbody>
    <p>The <cite>Dylan Reference Manual</cite> defines an interchange
    format for Dylan source files, but does not define an interchange
    format for Dylan libraries. Without such an agreed format,
    different Dylan development environments would find it difficult
    to import and build libraries developed using another Dylan
    environment. It would also be impossible to automate the
    process of importing a library into another environment.</p>
    
    <p>LID solves this problem. It allows programmers to describe
    Dylan library sources in a form that any Dylan environment should
    be able to understand. Dylan vendors have adopted LID to make it
    easier to port applications from one environment to another. </p>

    <p>Library interchange works by supplementing each set of library
    sources with a <term>LID file</term>. A LID file describes a Dylan
    library using a set of keyword statements. Together, these
    statements provide enough information to specify the information
    necessary to build a library from its source. This means that all
    Dylan libraries designed for interchange consist of at least two
    files: a LID file, and one or more files containing the library
    source code. </p>
    
    <p>Thus, a LID file performs a similar function to the
    <filepath>Makefile</filepath> used in some C and C++ development
    environments. </p>
    
    <p>LID files normally have the file extension
    <filepath>.lid</filepath>.</p>
  </conbody>
  
  <related-links>
    <link href="../reference/lid-file-keywords.xml" type="reference" format="xml">
      <linktext>LID File Keywords</linktext>
    </link>
    <link href="dylan-file-naming-conventions.xml" type="reference" format="xml">
      <linktext>Dylan File Naming Conventions</linktext>
    </link>
  </related-links>
</concept>
